Guide to the Estela and Ernesto Bravo Film and Video Collection TAM.616
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series VIII: Fidel: The Untold Story and Anecdotes about Fidel, 1995-2002
  - Video Segments on Elián González / Strimling, Arthur: Interview, circa 2000; cuid321 (Box 96, Dvd ref231)
    At the time this interview was conducted, Arthur Strimling was a theater teacher and the Artistic Director of Roots & Branches Theater.
    This video features an assortment of video segments recorded around the year 2000. The first clip briefly shows footage of Elián González receiving a book signed by Fidel Castro, the second features Castro walking in a parade, and the next features part of a speech by US Representative Maxine Waters welcoming Castro to New York City. At minute 7:28 the video switches to footage of an interview with Arthur Strimling. In the interview, Strimling talks about watching Castro speak in Harlem in 1959. He describes the crowds who gathered to see Castro and the reception Castro received from the media and political leaders. Strimling also talks about how his views on Castro changed over the years. He explains that although he has admiration for the economic revolution in Cuba, he is troubled by the country's human rights abuses and repression of political opposition.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:17:30.
  - Video Segments on Elián González / Strimling, Arthur: Interview, 1996; cuid323 (Box 96, Dvd ref1041)
    This video contains the same content as ref231. The first half features footage of Elián González and the second half features and interview with Arthur Strimling.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:17:28
  - "Yo Estuve Alli" (I Was There) - Selected Images (ICAIC), undated; cuid18227 (Box 6, Cassette ref233)
    According to the Estela and Ernesto Bravo, "Yo Estuve Alli" was a black and white documentary on the history of Cuba. It was not one of their films, but they included several clips from it in Fidel.
  - "Yo Estuve Alli" Images for Fidel, 2000 August 29; cuid18228 (Box 46, Cassette ref1024)
  - Photos of Young Fidel "Fotos Joven Fidel", undated; cuid18229 (Box 6, Cassette ref228)
  - "Unguarded Moments (1)", undated; cuid18230 (Box 9, Cassette ref196)
  - "Fidel en tennis, Juan Miguel, TV Cubana", 2000 September 8; cuid18231 (Box 8, Cassette ref183)
  - Fidel Speech: 17th Congress of the Workers Central Union of Cuba, undated; cuid18232 (Box 97, Dvd ref145)
    This video features a speech by Fidel Castro at the 17th Congress of the Workers Central Union of Cuba or Central de Trabajadores de Cuba (CTC). The footage does not contain a complete reporting of the speech, but rather starts and stops several times to focus on the crowd. Large portions of the speech can be heard in which Castro lectures on the virtues of socialism and the power of unity among the working class. He also criticizes the United States focusing on its foreign policy, treatment of the poor, and consumer capitalism.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:31:11.
  - Footage of Fidel Castro: At Che Guevara Memorial and Public Events, undated; cuid18233 (Box 97, Dvd ref232)
    This video features series of short clips of Fidel Castro at public events. The first event features Castro at a memorial for Ernesto "Che" Guevara. Other clips show him at rallies, greeting crowds, speaking with people on the street, and touring communities.
  - Medical Students, 1998 July 26; cuid18234 (Box Shared Tamiment 143, Betacam sp ref143)
  - "Fidel Comes to New York (Jon Alpert)", 1979; cuid18242
  - "UN-1", 2000 September 6; cuid18243 (Box 46, Cassette ref1025)
  - "Fidel Castro Special Effects", 1998 December 3; cuid18244 (Box 46, Cassette ref1036)
  - Miami landscapes - fruit stand (B-roll), undated; cuid18245 (Box 6, Cassette ref140)
  - Havana: On-the-Street Interviews, undated; cuid18246 (Box 97, Dvd ref238)
    This video features on-the-street interviews with people in Havana, Cuba. In these interviews Estela Bravo asks people what they think the future holds for Cuba. She specifically asks if they think Cuba will remain a socialist country, and whether they believe the Cuban government will retain power after Fidel Castro's leadership ends. The majority express their belief that Cuban government will remain intact. Individuals on the street also discuss their opinions about the Cuba socialism, and the reasons they have stayed in the country when many others have left.
  - "Havana", undated; cuid18247 (Box 9, Cassette ref40)
  - Images of Havana (B-roll), undated; cuid18249 (Box 6, Cassette ref216)
  - " Miami, Siro-setup, Visuals, Dominoes" (B-roll), undated; cuid18250 (Box 67, Cassette ref994)
  - Rosenberg, Alex, 1996 August 20; cuid18253 (Box 39, Cassette ref11)
- Series IX: Flotilla to Cuba, 1993
  Released in 1993, Flotilla to Cuba shows a fleet of small vessels setting out from Key West, Florida, to Cuba, carrying food and medicine in a humanitarian gesture sponsored by US citizens. The film shows the flotilla's arrival in Cuba and the distribution of its cargo to hospitals in Havana, but also reveals divisions within the Cuban community in Florida. This series contains a full-length documentary, as well as raw footage of the flotilla.
  - Flotilla to Cuba, 1993; cuid387 (Box 96, Dvd ref1272)
    This video contains a complete version of the short film Flotilla to Cuba. Video quality of this tape is intermittently poor.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:12:17.
  - Footage: Flotilla to Cuba, circa 1993; cuid18254 (Box 66, Cassette ref1341)
    This is a full-length version of the film Flotilla to Cuba. This film is in Spanish.
  - Key West Flotilla footage #2, 1993 April 24; cuid18255 (Box 54, Cassette ref1258)
  - Key West Flotilla footage #3, 1993 April 24; cuid18256 (Box 98, Dvd ref1237)
    This video begins with an interview with a mother and daughter in Key West, Florida preparing medical supplies to send in a 1993 humanitarian flotilla to Cuba. The mother and daughter discuss their reasons for supporting the flotilla and express their frustration at the people opposing it. They criticize the United States embargo against Cuba, and contend the that flotilla is a matter of human rights not politics. The video then shows footage of people loading a boat with supplies. At minute 14:10, Bravo interviews a group of people opposing the flotilla who argue that the goods will be taken by the Cuban government and sold to tourists. They express their doubt that the Cuban people will receive the goods, and instead express their fear that Castro will use the aid to control the people.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:28:15.
  - Key West Flotilla footage #4, 1993 April 24; cuid18257 (Box 54, Cassette ref1262)
  - Flotilla: Footage of Hemingway Marina and Pediatric Hospital "Cassette #6", 1993; cuid18258 (Box 98, Dvd ref1263)
    This video documents the arrival of a flotilla of supplies in Cuba. It begins with an interview with the crew of one of the boats who talk about the rough waters on their journey across the Strait of Florida. The footage then changes to a larger ship of supplies being unloaded onto a Red Cross truck. It features an interview with one of the Red Cross organizers as well as an organizer from the Key West-based group Basta. The end of video features a second interview with the spokesman from Basta at a children's hospital where many of the supplies were delivered. He explains that the purpose of the event at the hospital is to prove that the supplies are being delivered directly to the people.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:31:13.
  - "Llegado a la Habana (Marina Hemingway) Flotilla Robles", 1993 April 25; cuid18259 (Box 63, Cassette ref1102)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:32:29.
    This video contains interviews with U.S. citizens who traveled from Key West, Florida in a flotilla to bring vitamins, food, and other resources to Havana, Cuba. The video begins with seven minutes of footage of the boats and people talking on the dock. The people are discussing the weather and difficulty of travel. Interviewees describe how they acquired government permission for the trip and their reasons for participating.
  - Flotilla 2 "Javier Diet Foods", 1993; cuid18260 (Box 54, Cassette ref1259)
  - Flotilla "Anti-Diet Brinkley", 1993; cuid18261 (Box 54, Cassette ref1261)
  - Flotilla "Javier Features show logos", 1993; cuid18262 (Box 54, Cassette ref2157)
  - "Flotilla 6 Aireye VHS Dub", 1993; cuid18263 (Box 54, Cassette ref1238)
  - Flotilla, 1993; cuid18264 (Box 54, Cassette ref1260)
- Series X: Free to Fly: The US-Cuba Link, 2004
  Subtitled "A History of 25 Years of Travel Restrictions," the 33-minute film Free to Fly: The US-Cuba Link tells the story of efforts to maintain links between the Cuban and American people. Also documented are the activities of many of the anti-Castro groups in Florida and in New Jersey who violently opposed travel between the United States and Cuba. Appearing in the film are US politicians including Republican Senator and former Representative from Arizona Jeff Flake; Republican former Senator and Representative from Idaho, Larry Craig; Democratic former Representative from Massachusetts, Bill Delahunt; and Democratic Massachusetts Representative, Jim McGovern. In the documentary they contend that travel between the countries builds openness and understanding; strengthens family ties; fosters cultural exchange, tourism and trade; and is a constitutional right for all Americans. No raw footage associated with the film is available. Only a completed version of the documentary is included in this series.
  - Free to Fly: The US-Cuba Link, 2004; cuid18265 (Box 73, Dvd 3)
    This is a full-length version of the film Free to Fly: The US-Cuba Link.
- Series XI: Holy Father and Gloria, 1985-1991
  Estela Bravo's 1987 film Holy Father and Gloria El Santo Padre y la Gloria won many awards including Best Documentary on Current Affairs at the San Francisco International Film Festival; Gold Plaque Award at the Chicago International Film Festival; and Best Documentary at the American Film Institute Global Village Festival in New York.
  Carmen Gloria Quintana Arancibia (1968- ) is a Chilean woman who became a symbol of hope for democracy in Chile to many Chileans after she received an embrace and encouragement from Pope John Paul II in 1987. On July 2,1986, Quintana, along with a young photographer, Rodrigo Andres Rojas de Negri, were participating in a student protest in Santiago. They were attacked and beaten by a patrol of military police, soaked with gasoline, and set on fire. De Negri died of his burns. Gloria suffered second and third degree burns over 62% of her body; she was critically ill and was moved to a hospital in Canada. Although she survived, Gloria was badly disfigured from her burns. When the Pope visited Chile in 1987, she returned and was able to meet with the pontiff in Santiago.
  The 43-minute documentary Holy Father and Gloria (El Santo Padre y la Gloria) was released in 1987 and captures the turbulence of Chile under the Pinochet dictatorship. It traces the story of Carmen Gloria Quintana and her 1987 journey back to Chile to see the Pope. In addition to footage of the Pope's visit and the ongoing protests the documentary includes interviews with Quintana and many others. Among the voices captured are those of elites, particularly young people, who supported the Pinochet government and felt the protests were unnecessary. Footage in this series includes shots of Quintana touring Chile, speeches by the Pope, interviews with Quintana and other Chileans, and historical footage contextualizing Chilean politics.
  - El Santo Padre y la Gloria, 1987; cuid18266 (Box 73, Dvd 10)
    This is a full-length version of the film Holy Father and Gloria. This film is in Spanish and contains subtitles in English.
  - Holy Father and Gloria, 1987; 2012.044 (Reel ref2158_01, Reel ref2158_02)
  - Holy Father and Gloria, 1987; 2013.014; 1 Reels (Reel ref2165)
  - Holy Father and Gloria, 1987; cuid18267 (Box 97, Dvd ref961)
    This video contains a complete version of the documentary Holy Father and Gloria. Video quality is poor at the beginning of the video.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:44:08.
  - Holy Father and Gloria, Spanish, 1991 January 14; cuid18269 (Box 43, Cassette ref960)
  - Holy Father and Gloria "Version 1 First Edit", 1987; cuid18270 (Box 55, Cassette ref1273)
  - "El Santo Padre y La Gloria 42 minutes (Español)", 1987; cuid18271 (Box 61, Cassette ref1365)
  - Quintana, Carmen Gloria: Arrival in Chile, 1987; cuid18272 (Box 98, Dvd ref1361)
    This video predominantly features footage of Carmen Gloria Quintana arriving in Chile among crowds of supporters. It contains brief segments in which Quintana speaks with reporters and describes the medical treatment she received in Canada, and expresses her support of the Chilean youth movement. It contains footage of Quintana at rallies and a Catholic mass. The last 15 minutes feature Quintana and her supporters outside of a jail attempting to gain entry and meet with political prisoners.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:50:25.
  - Quintana, Carmen Gloria: Interview (Debryando Street), 1987 May 4; cuid388 (Box 95, Dvd ref809)
    This video features youth in Chile celebrating the return of Carmen Gloria Quintana, and a brief interview with Quintana. The first several minutes feature children drawing doves and other tributes to Quintana on the street. At minute 2:58 the video changes to an interview with Quintana. She discusses her hope of meeting with the Pope, and her surprise at the warm welcome she received upon her return. She says that she hopes to continue fighting and speaking out against the dictatorship of Augusto Pinochet, but acknowledges that protest is still very difficult. She also discusses a button featuring the Rodrigo Andres Rojas de Negri, who died when they were both attacked by members of the Chilean military and burned. She explains that she hopes to be a representative of Rojas's memory. At minute 10:56 the footage changes to Chilean youths discussing a mural of Quintana and Rojas, painted at the location where they were attacked. A young woman and young man speak with Bravo about the significance of Quintana and Rojas to the youth movement in Chile.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:20:27.
  - Footage: "Carmen, Rodrigo, Pope;" "Completo", 1987; cuid18273 (Box 60, Cassette ref1362)
  - Footage: "Funeral Rodrigo, Cemetery, Carmen Gloria", 1987; cuid18274 (Box 67, Cassette ref1364)
    According to Estela Bravo, this video contains 13 minutes of footage of the funeral of Rodrigo Rojas, followed by brief footage of young people being arrested. It also contains pictures of Carmen Gloria before she was burned. Finally, there is footage of a young woman - Valesa - who left Chile with her family but was allowed to return later. This footage is from the film Returning to Chile.
  - Footage: Parque O'Higgins and Carmen Gloria, 1987; cuid18275 (Box 67, Cassette ref1366)
    According to Bravo, this video contains footage of the Pope speaking at Parque O'Higgins followed by Carmen Gloria in her home in Chile, with family and friends.
    Parque O'Higgins is a public park in the center of Santiago, Chile. Pope John Paul II (in his 1987 visit) led a beautification ceremony for Saint Teresa of the Andes. Because of the violence that broke out between the Chilean police force and crowds protesting Pinochet's dictatorship, the ceremony was suspended until the situation calmed.
  - Footage: O'Higgins Park, Santiago: Protests at Pope's Mass, 1987; cuid18276 (Box 97, Dvd ref837)
    This video begins with footage of violent clashes between the police and protestors at O'Higgins Park in Santiago, Chile where Pope John Paul II delivered Mass to a large crowd in 1987. The footage shows protestors building makeshift barriers and throwing objects while police try to disperse them. The footage focuses primarily on the crowd, and does not show the Pope speaking, although he can be heard through a loudspeaker. The video features several on-the-street interviews: one with a man opposed to the protests, one with a local journalist, and one with a young protester. The end of this video also features an interview with exiled Chilean Socialist leader Clodomiro Almeyda. In the interview Almeyda discusses why he chose to return to Chile during the Pope's visit to the country.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 01:02:33.
  - Footage: "Chile, Students, Gloria", 1987; cuid790 (Box 98, Dvd ref1367)
    This video features interviews with three different groups of students in Chile. Estela Bravo asks the students, who are from middle and upper-class schools, about their opinions of Chilean President Augusto Pinochet, Pope John Paul II's visit, and the attack on Carmen Gloria Quintana. Students from the various groups express different opinions on these topics, and many of the students who come from upper-class households express their support of Pinochet. They argue that the people protesting his government are mistaken and supporters of terrorism. Several students express their admiration for Pinochet, and contend that he saved the country from communism. Other students express their dislike of Pinochet, and contend that the students who support him are uninformed and are not in a position to understand the political situation of the country.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:57:28.
  - Footage: Chilean Boy and the Police, 1987 March 4; cuid18277 (Box 98, Dvd ref1373)
    This video begins with footage of a mother trying to talk to Chilean police about her son. She explains that she heard that her son, who was 9 years old at the time the footage was recorded, was injured by police after they chased him into a house. The woman attempts to find out what happened to her son and where he was taken, but the police do not give her any information. The video then focuses on the house where the boy was attacked. The family in the house explains that they police chased the boy, broke down their door, and hit the young boy in the head causing him to bleed significantly. Several of the children and adults in the house describe witnessing the event. They also talk about police treatment of the poor and substandard living conditions in their community.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:21:18.
  - Footage: "Pinochet greets Pope at the airport", 1987; cuid18278 (Box 52, Cassette ref1210)
  - Footage: Rojas Grave and Interview with son of Orlando Letelier, 1987; cuid389 (Box 95, Dvd ref810)
    Juan Pablo Letelier was the son of Orlando Letelier. Orlando Letelier was a Chilean diplomat under the government of Salvador Allende. He left Chile as a refugee of the dictatorship of Augusto Pinochet, and was assassinated by Pinochet's secret police in Washington D.C. in 1976.
    This video mostly features an interview with Juan Pablo Letelier. The first few seconds of the video contain footage of the grave of Chilean dissident Rodrigo Andres Rojas de Negri. It quickly changes to an interview with Letelier, which begins with a discussion about his early life and his father's assassination. He discusses leaving Chile when he was 3 years old, and returning to Chile later in life. He also talks about his involvement in leftist political movements in Chile and his participations in Chile's Socialist Youth. He discusses the significance of the visit of Pope John Paul II in 1987, and the 1989 general elections. Letelier talks at length about the political climate in Chile at the end of the 1980s discussing the country's transition to democracy and the influence of youth activism. The video quality is poor in many places.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:20:58.
  - Footage: College Stadium (the Pope speaking and Carmen Gloria in the audience) and Cemetery, 1987; cuid18279 (Box 67, Cassette ref1368)
  - Footage: Police Brutality, 1985 September 4; cuid18280 (Box 67, Cassette ref1369)
  - Footage: Carmen Gloria Quintana Complete Visit Jail, circa 1987; cuid18281 (Box 98, Dvd ref1370)
    This video features footage of Carmen Gloria Quintana attempting to gain entry into a jail in Chile to meet with political prisoners. A spokesman for Quintana explains she is there to express her solidarity with prisoners. The bulk of the footage features a crowd waiting outside the jail hoping to gain entry. This video duplicates content contained on video ref1361.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:20:03.
  - Footage: "Carmen Gloria in victory", 1987; cuid18282 (Box 97, Dvd ref811)
    This video begins with brief footage of two Chilean youths at a mural memorializing the attack on Carmen Gloria Quintana and Rodrigo Rojas who were burned by Chilean military police in 1986. The video then changes to footage of Quintana arriving at a rally in her honor. Much of this footage features shots of the crowd gathered in anticipation of Quintana's arrival. At minute 13:00 Quintana addresses the crowd and describes her encounter with the military, in which she and Rojas were doused with gasoline and then lit on fire. At the time of her speech, she explains that it has been 10 months since the event and notes that she has been left badly disfigured and Rojas has died.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:21:09.
  - Footage: March Final Against Torture, 1987 February 4; cuid18283 (Box 98, Dvd ref1371)
    The beginning of this video features an interview with a man and a woman in a church in Chile. They discuss their involvement in the resistance movement against the Pinochet government and the violence they have witnessed in the country. The interview focuses on the government's use of torture against citizens. The woman shares specific examples of torture used against Chilean citizens, discuss police interrogation methods, and describes the psychological effects of state-sponsored violence. At minute 12:00 the video features a demonstration against the government, and protestors can be seen clashing briefly with the police. Bravo interviews members of the crowd about why they are at the protest, and about their expectations for the upcoming 1987 visit of Pope John Paul II.
  - National Stadium / Pope Compilation, 1987; cuid18284 (Box 20, Cassette ref550)
  - "Pope, Chile, Street, Carmen Gloria, Funeral Rodrigo," and Others, 1987; cuid18285 (Box 60, Cassette ref1363)
  - Carmen Gloria " Ernesto's Copy", 1987; cuid18286 (Box 43, Cassette ref841)
  - "2 Carmen Gloria Completa", 1987; cuid18287 (Box 1, Betacam ref253)
  - "El Santo Padre y la Gloria", 1987; cuid18288 (Box 19, U-matic ref630)
  - "El Santo Padre y la Gloria", 1987; cuid18289 (Box 1, Betacam ref684)
  - "TV Espanola Programa Editado - Pinochet - the Pope - Chile - Carmen Gloria", 1987; cuid18290 (Box 37, Cassette ref719)
  - "Hotel Capri - press conference - Estela Bravo - Juan Vilar", circa 1987; cuid18291 (Box 38, Cassette ref720)
  - "Torture photos - Pinochet speech", circa 1987; cuid18292 (Box 37, Cassette ref726)
  - "Pepe Carrasco CNN Pinochet", circa 1986; cuid18293 (Box 97, Dvd ref802)
    Jose Humberto "Pepe" Carrasco Tapia (1943-1986) was a Chilean journalist opposed to the military dictatorship of Augusto Pinochet. He was assassinated on September 7, 1986.